Francis J. O' Malley Papers
University of Notre Dame Archives
Francis J. O' Malley Papers
1932-1974.
FOM
O' Malley, Francis J., 1911-1974.
12 linear feet. 2 linear inches of photographs.
University of Notre Dame Archives Notre Dame, Indiana 46556
Scope and Content
Correspondence, photographs, published and unpublished writings by O'Malley, and material relating to his teaching activities, including student papers, class record books, and lectures. Correspondents include Willa Cather, Desmond Fitzgerald, Jacques Maritain, Edward Goerner, Edwin O'Connor, and Hannah Arendt.
Background
Teacher of English at the University of Notre Dame 1934-1974; managing, and later associate, editor of The Review of Politics.
Review of Politics (Organization).; Cather, Willa; Fitzgerald, Desmond, 1889-1947.; Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973.; Goerner, Edward Alfred, 1929-; O'Connor, Edwin.; Arendt, Hannah.; O'Malley, Frank, 1909-1974.
Related Material
Department of Information Services Records
Notre Dame Life Photograph Collection
Notre Dame Magazine Records
Notre Dame Printed and Reference Material Dropfiles
Richard Sullivan Papers
Notre Dame Audio-Visual and Oversize Graphics Collection
- Francis J. O'Malley: Manuscripts, CFOM
  - Published Writings by O'Malley, 1941-1973; CFOM 1/, 30/; Articles on literary and religious topics published in The Review of Politics, America, The Critic, and other journals and anthologies. The series includes reprints of the articles. O'Malley's unpublished writings are filed with other background material for his lectures (CFOM 10-13).
    - Note in Devere Plunkett's handwriting: "F. O'M wrote articles for Orate Fratres such as 'The Crown of Paul Claudel' (prior to 1944)", CFOM 1/01
    - Precis of paper " The Images of Man in Modern Christian Literature", CFOM 1/02
    - Program of Symposium on Religion and Modern Society, February 16 and 17 O'Malley to deliver lecture "Modern Literature and the Religious Attitude Toward Life," Note from L(eo) R. W(ard)., CFOM 1/03
    - "Some Thoughts on the Vocation of the Layman," note attached in Devere Plunkett's handwriting: "Probably Frank's paper--- Date c. 1969-1970? Occasion not known." Plunkett's assumption is doubtful; it appears to be an unidentified student paper., CFOM 1/04
    - "The Political Perversion of Art," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 3, No. 2, pp. 243-49, April 1941., CFOM 1/05
    - "That Which Demoralizes Us," Radio Address, WSBT, South Bend, Indiana, October 24, 1941 given under the auspices of Fight for Freedom, Inc., CFOM 1/06
    - "Religion and The Modern Mind," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 4, No.4, pp. 489-507, October 1942 (additional copy cut from journal), CFOM 1/07
    - "Tribute to Jacques Maritain," Review, reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 5, No. 2, pp. 243-46, April 1943., CFOM 1/08
    - "The Education of Man," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 6, No. 1, pp. 3-17, January 1944. Handwritten notes by O'Malley re: education inserted within the article., CFOM 1/09
    - "The Evangelism of Georges Bernanos," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 6, No.4, pp. 403-21, October 1944., CFOM 1/10
    - "The American Idealist," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 7, No. 4, pp. 267-69, July, 1945., CFOM 1/11
    - "The Plight of the Soul," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 7, No. 3, pp. 368-78, July 1945. Inserted within are O'Malley's handwritten notes on "The Philosophical Study of Literature.", CFOM 1/12
    - "Present Tutoring Points in American Literature," Issues by the Institute for Religious and Social Studies, New York, 1946., CFOM 1/13
    - "The Passion of Leon Bloy,' Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 10, No.1, pp. 100-15, January 1948., CFOM 1/14
    - "The Blood of Robert Lowell," Reprint Renascence, Vol.II, No.1, Fall 1949. Second copy with correspondence inserted: John D. McCabe to Francis J. O'Malley, April 19, 1973., CFOM 1/15
    - "The Faustianism of John Milton." Proceedings of the American Catholic Philosophical Association, Vol. XXIV, April 11, 12, 1950 (Washington D.C., Catholic University of America, 1950) pp. 123-32. Typed manuscript included., CFOM 1/16
    - "James T. Farrell: Two Twilight Images," Reproduced from Fifty Years of the American Novel 1900-1950 Ed. Harold C. Gardiner, S.J. (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons) pp. 237-56., CFOM 1/17
    - "The American Novel Through Fifty Years: XI James T. Farrell," America, Vol. 85, No. 12, June 23, 1951, pp. 311-13., CFOM 1/18
    - The Committee on International Relations symposium on "Religion and the Crisis of the Twentieth Century," April 22, O'Malley to deliver lecture "The Church and Modern Literature." 1953, CFOM 1/19
    - "The Culture of the Church," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 16, No. 2, pp. 131-54, April 1954., CFOM 1/20
    - "Teaching the Twentieth-Century Power World," Address given at Danforth Conference, Camp Miniwanca, Michigan, September1957., CFOM 1/21
    - "The Teaching Function of an American University," Conference on Higher Education, University of Illinois, Robert Allerton Park, June 21-24, 1958, pp.31-35. Correspondence inserted: Royden Dangerfield to Frank O'Malley, March 19, 1959. Note: Lou Hasley to Frank O'Malley, n.d., CFOM 1/22
    - "The Thinker in the Church: The Spirit of Newman," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 21, No. 1, pp. 5-23, January 1959., CFOM 1/23
    - "The Wasteland of William Blake," Reproduced from The Image of Man, The Review of Politics Reader (Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, January, 1959), pp. 291-310. Letter attached: Royce Moch to Waldemar Gurian, June 11, 1947., CFOM 1/24
    - "The Catholic Contribution to the Arts," The Critic, Vol. XX, No. 2, October-November 1961, pp. 56-57., CFOM 1/25
    - "The Thinker in the Church II: The Urgencies of Romano Guardini," Reprint The Review of Politics, Vol. 25, No. 4, pp. 451-59, October, 1963., CFOM 1/26
    - "The Sacredness of Persons," The University of Portland Review, Vol. XVI, 1964, pp. 12-19., CFOM 1/27
    - Writings of O'Malley, CFOM 30/04
    - Writings of O'Malley, CFOM 30/05
    - Writings of O'Malley, CFOM 30/06
    - Writings of O'Malley, CFOM 30/07
  - Teaching Records, 1934-1974; CFOM 2-22/, 29/; This series contains material relating to O'Malley`s activities as a member of the Notre Dame faculty (English Department).
    - Lectures and Speeches, 1930s-1970s; CFOM 2-13/, 29/; Texts, notes, and background material for class lectures and speeches to outside groups. The background material consists of articles, by O`Malley and others, and student papers. The lecture texts and notes are arranged alphabetically by title or subject. The background material is arranged separately, but in the same manner. Some of the lecture texts appear to be unpublished manuscripts by O'Malley. Much of the material is undated.
      - "Some Observations on the Way of American Fiction," American literature lecture, English 297s., CFOM 2/01
      - "Present Turning Points in American Literature," lecture., CFOM 2/02
      - American Realists and Romanticists "The Romantic Writers." introductory lecture "The Realists," introductory lecture "Emily Dickinson," lecture Bibliographic Note Cards Modern Art Outline, Literary Criticism Bibliography, Literary Criticism Ruck Suckow an American Apathy "Approximations," 5-page typed paper by unidentified author, CFOM 2/03
      - St. Thomas Aquinas, CFOM 2/04
      - Notes on Aristotle, CFOM 2/05
      - Speech re: Jim Armstrong upon his retirement, CFOM 2/06
      - Matthew Arnold Lectures: Victorian Humanists I: "The Problem of Poetry and Personality and Life" II: "Arnold and the Anarchy of Culture" III: "The Reformer of Reformation", CFOM 2/07
      - "Notes on Francis Bacon", CFOM 2/08
      - Belief and Art (Poetry): notes, CFOM 2/09
      - "Bergson, St. Thomas and Cardinal Newman: The Intuitive Method", CFOM 2/10
      - "The Evangelism of George Bernanos," longhand draft, CFOM 2/11
      - "The Evangelism of George Bernanos," Typed copy (Published in the Review of Politics.), CFOM 2/12
      - "William Blake: The Poet of the Underworld," unidentified author, not by O'Malley List of "Problems in Blake" "Blake's Notions of Art" Notes on Blake Blake's attack on the intellect "Blake: An Introduction," lecture, CFOM 2/13
      - "The Religion of William Blake," lecture, CFOM 2/14
      - "The Wasteland of William Blake," typed copy and reprint of it published in Review of Politics, Vol. 9, No. 2, (April 1947), pp. 183-204., CFOM 2/15
      - "The Vitalitism of Butler, Nietzsche and Bergson, " lecture, CFOM 2/16
      - "Carlyle I: The Formation of His Idea, His _______," Outline The Victorian Humanists "Carlyle III: The significance of Carlyle and the Dichotomy in the Nineteenth Century Culture," lecture, The Victorian Humanists "Carlyle I:" lecture "Carlyle's Basis for the Religion of Work," by Milton Fisk, student paper, CFOM 2/17
      - "Carlyle II: The Inarticulate Divineness of the Past and Present (The Impulse of God in Man and History)," lecture, The Victorian Humanists Student Paper, author unidentified, one typed page, on Victorian Humanism Proust and Bergson notes. "The Windhover: To Christ Our Lord," pages2-4 of a student paper by Milton Fisk on Gerard Manley Hopkins' poem, CFOM 2/18
      - "The Catholic and Literature," speech given at St. Mary's College, CFOM 2/19
      - Catholic College: "The Nature of the Catholic College," paper prepared during 1942-45 discussion of a laymen's college, CFOM 2/20
      - Catholic Literature: Annotated bibliography, CFOM 2/21
      - Catholic Novelists "Sean O'Faolain and Catholic Calvinism": The Modern Novel: A Catholic Point of View" by Sean O'Faolain "Arthur Rimbaud," 9 paged of a longer paper, author unidentified "Problems of Catholic Novelists and of Catholic Readers of Novels," by J. Lanigan, one page paper "Francois Mauriac," lecture "Mauriac: A Study in Theory and Practice," by Sister Mary Owen Kleinhenz, S.N.D., August 11, 1949, 8 page paper Student (?) paper on Mauriac's "A Woman of the Pharisees," 5 pages Notes for lecture on Mauriac an Bloy, one page Letter: Sister Moira, S.C.N., to Esther ______, n.d. which mentions O'Malley, CFOM 2/22
      - "Catholic Values in a Disintegrating World: The Renascence of the Novelist and the Poet," paper, also used as a lecture on Virginia Woolf. See also "Novel, Renascence of," and "Woolf, Virginia.", CFOM 2/23
      - "The Catholic World View," Chapter IV (pp. 37-41) of larger work, CFOM 2/24
      - Catholic Writers "The Real Type of Modern Catholic Critic," 18 handwritten pages "Sheed and Ward Samplers: 3: Jacques Maritain" (Sheed and Ward: New York, 1936), pamphlet Printed Excerpt: "The Honest People" Fastened to a sheet of paper labled "Peguy" George Bernanos, "Mediocrity an Sanctity: The function of saints and martyrs," Commonweal, December 17, 1943, pp. 220-25. Leon Bloy, "Four Comfortable Sayings," transcription of article in The Colosseum, December 1935, pp. 257-61. "Maritain's Pilgrimage to Bloy," excerpt from Commonweal, August 15, 1941, pp. 393-94. Galley proofs of article on "Leon Bloy (1846-1917)" containing excerpts from The Woman Who Was Poor and Letters to his Fiance, CFOM 2/25
      - Christian Civilization: page 25 of unidentified larger work, CFOM 3/01
      - "The Christian Interpretation of History and Society," lectures I, II, III, IV: Christian Interpretation of History and Society.", CFOM 3/02
      - "The Christian in the World, "also" in his Church, in his family, in his work.", CFOM 3/03
      - "The Concept of Christmas", CFOM 3/04
      - Claudel Notes lectures on Claudel "The Crown of Paul Claudel," essay "The Hostage: A Passion Play," Unidentified student paper "Rimbaud," lecture notes Table of Contents to a five-chapter work (of O'Malley?) Student paper on Claudel, 25 pages, CFOM 3/05
      - Claudel Notes on Claudel's The Tidings Brought to Mary and program of a production of the play at Mt. St. Scholastica Production notes for The Tidings Brought to Mary, CFOM 3/06
      - Claudel "The Achievement of Claudel," lecture? Title page of student paper, "Review of Readings and Study: Modern Catholic Authors," by Brother david Warnke, C.S.C. Unidentified student paper, 6 pages on Claudel "Chapter IV: Violaine Woman of Miracles," pp. 41-51. "A Child of Peace," unidentified author, pp. 32-42., CFOM 3/07
      - Coleridge "A Note on the Romantic Spirit in Coleridge," 14 pages of a larger paper by an unidentified author, CFOM 3/08
      - College of Arts and Letters Proposal to the College of Arts and Letters, April 16, 1965 re: Personal Advancement for Selected Students, CFOM 3/09
      - "The Catholic in Contemporary American Civilization," Commencement Address given by O'Malley at Aquinas College, May 31, 1953., CFOM 3/10
      - "New Beginnings, New Years for Our High School," Commencement Address given by O'Malley at Clinton High School, Mass., June 20, 1962., CFOM 3/11
      - "The Vast, the General Question," Commencement Address given by O'Malley at Mt. St. Scholastica College, 1944., CFOM 3/12
      - Commencement Address by O'Malley, University of Notre Dame, July 31, 1956., CFOM 3/13
      - Lectures on James Fenimore Cooper "Romanticism: Summary" "James Fenimore Cooper: Lecture I: A National American Culture and Literature" "James Fenimore Cooper: Lecture II: The Personal Cooper" "James Fenimore Cooper: Lecture III: The Successful Cooper", CFOM 3/14
      - Cooper and Poe, Philosophy of Literature Lectures "James Fenimore Cooper: Lecture IV: Cooper's Social and Political Ideas;" Bibliography; Second title paper, Lecture V:Cooper's Social and Political Ideas as given in The American Democrat in 1838 "James Fenimore Cooper: Lecture IV: The Critical Cooper" "Cooper Bibliography" "Poe, the Fakir", CFOM 3/15
      - Studies in Criticism: Notes, CFOM 3/16
      - "The Culture of the Church," Address to the Wranglers, May 21, 1951, handwritten, CFOM 3/17
      - "The Culture of the Church," by Frank O'Malley, typed draft, CFOM 3/18
      - "Darwin, Huxley, and Haechel," lecture, CFOM 3/19
      - Christopher Dawson "Lecture V, English 285: Part 1: Christopher Dawson," Page 4 missing "Lecture VI, English 285: Part 2: Christopher Dawson" "The Study of Christian Culture as a Means of Education," by Christopher Dawson, reprint from "Lumen Vitae," Vol. I, No. 1 (1950) John Mulloy to Mr. Frank O'Malley, August 19, 1953, with enclosed excerpts from Dawson lectures, CFOM 3/20
      - "II Joseph De Maistre and the Romantic Movement in The Religious Underworld:" "Joseph De Maistre: The Counter Revolution," lecture "Christianity and Europe," by Friedrich von Hardenberg (Novalis), translated by Eva Maria Neumeyer "The Church and the Revolution," by Christopher Dawson, CFOM 3/21
      - "Descartes and His System", CFOM 3/22
      - "John Dos Passos and the Wasteland," American literature lecture, CFOM 3/23
      - Theodore Dreiser: notes, CFOM 3/24
      - John Dryden: Philosophy of Literature Lecture "John Dryden: The Man of Good Faith," unidentified student paper "Lecture I: John Dryden: His Skepticism" "II: John Dryden: Fideism", CFOM 3/25
      - "How to Educate an American", CFOM 4/01
      - Lecture Notes on Education: Newman, Hutchins General lectures on education and the university Outlines, "Analogues: Newman and Hutchins", CFOM 4/02
      - T.S. Eliot: Notes, particularly concerning "The Wasteland;" and a review of "The Wasteland" by Charles J. Kirby Published in Scrip, CFOM 4/03
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture I: Emerson, the Expanding American" (or "Emerson The American Scholar, Lecture I: Emerson, the Man of America"), CFOM 4/04
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture II: The Scholar" "Lecture III: The Self-Reliant Optimist", CFOM 4/05
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture IV: Cloudy Circle (Religious and Philosophical Conceptions)", CFOM 4/06
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture V: The Cloudy Circle, Part II", CFOM 4/07
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture VI: The Organic (His Theory of Art and His Practices in Poetry)", CFOM 4/08
      - Emerson: The Pragmatic Romanticist "Lecture VII: The Liberal", CFOM 4/09
      - Emerson: Student Paper, unidentified author, used as lecture, CFOM 4/10
      - English Poets: Bibliography of W.H. Auden and Stephen Spender, CFOM 4/11
      - James T. Farrell "James T. Farrell: Two Twilight Images," By Frank O'Malley reproduced fron Fifty Years of the American Novel 1900-50, Ed. Harold C. Gardiner, S.J. (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons) Typed manuscript of same paper Handwritten draft of same paper, CFOM 4/12
      - William Faulkner "William Faulkner, The Bats in the Violent Light" American literature lecture, CFOM 4/13
      - Freedom Fight for Freedom Speech by O'Malley: "That Which Demoralizes Us," October 24, 1941. Two copies, CFOM 4/14
      - Freedom "Freedom of Choice," A Proposal to the Wranglers, CFOM 4/15
      - Freedom "The Nature of Freedom," Speech, Fall, 1956(?), CFOM 4/16
      - Guardini Notes "The Church and the Catholic and The Spirit of the Liturgy," An Address to the Architects of Notre Dame, November 22, 1954. J.B. Gremillion, "Interview with Romano Guardini," America, November 15, 1958, pp. 194-95., CFOM 4/17
      - Guardini "The Thinker in the Church II: The Urgencies of Romano Guardini," handwritten draft of O'Malley's article published in the Review of Politics, Vol. 25, No. 4, pp. 451-59 (October, 1963), CFOM 4/18
      - "The Philosophy of Thomas Hardy," lecture, CFOM 4/19
      - "The Harvard Report: Some Notes and Comments", CFOM 4/20
      - "Hawthorne: The Haunted Mind, the Anti-Puritan," lecture, CFOM 4/21
      - "Hemingway: The Heap of Broken Images," lecture, CFOM 4/22
      - "Integral History," Paper by unidentified author, CFOM 4/23
      - Gerard Manley Hopkins Poems of Gerard Manley Hopkins, ed. Robert Bridges "Mary the Dawn," poem by unidentified author "Three Poets Discuss New Verse Forms: The Correspondence of Gerard Manley Hopkins, Robert Bridges, and Coventry Patmore," by Derek Patmore "The Library of Congress Division of Bibliography: Gerard Manley Hopkins, 1844-1889, A bibliographical list, 1940." "On the Centenary of the Poet's Birth, and Series of Lectures to Honor Gerard Manley Hopkins, 1844-1889." outline by O'Malley, CFOM 4/24
      - G.M. Hopkins Lectures "Hopkins Centenary Lectures, I, The Visible World: Sensibility" "Hopkins Centenary Lectures, II, The Visible World:Judgement" "The Windhover--G.M. Hopkins--a penetration," lecture "Hopkins Centenary Lectures, IV: Spiritual Form" Chapter III (pp. 46-52) of larger thesis on Hopkins, author unidentified., CFOM 4/25
      - "A few notes on G.M. Hopkins," re: Commemorative lectures, CFOM 4/26
      - "The Theology of 'The Wreck of the Deutschland,'" speech delivered at St. Mary's College "The Wreck of the Deutschland," Parts II, IV, and V (pp. 14-39, 58-68, 79-82) of a thesis on Hopkins, author unidentified., CFOM 4/27
      - "A Note on G.M. Hopkins' The Wreck", CFOM 4/28
      - G.M. Hopkins Centenary lecture material Unidentified student paper re: "The Wreck of the Deutschland" Pasquale Di Pasquale, "The Influence of Duns Scotus on G.M. Hopkins," B.A. Thesis, 1955., CFOM 4/29
      - "The Humanist Reaction Against Naturalistic Values," philosophy of literature lecture, CFOM 4/30
      - "Values and A. Huxley," lecture, CFOM 4/31
      - Impressionism Lecture material, chapter XI, pp. 1-16, of larger work; and Bibliography, CFOM 5/01
      - Individualism "The God We Left Behind Us," pp. 1-20 of longer work including prologue poem, "The Catholic Men," (Filed in folder labeled "Talk on Individualism and its Perversions in Society"), CFOM 5/02
      - "The Frustration of Human Nature in James, Conrad, and George Moore (with a note on Romares)," lecture, CFOM 5/03
      - Notes on James Joyce- Notes, clippings, and a student paper by Duggan, CFOM 5/04
      - Special papers on James Joyce "James Joyce and the Significance of Human Action," lecture "Dove in the Thicket: The Liturgy of James Joyce," by Don Connors, student paper, CFOM 5/05
      - "James Joyce, Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man," lecture, CFOM 5/06
      - "A Common Confusion," by Franz Kafka: O'Malley outline, CFOM 5/07
      - Kafka lectures, CFOM 5/08
      - Kafka, Silone, Mauriac: Part of a Lecture, CFOM 5/09
      - Kant Lectures "Kant:" Philosophy "Kant" "Summary of Kant, Fuller's Commentary", CFOM 5/10
      - "President Kennedy: An American in Search of Civilization", CFOM 5/11
      - Archbishop John B. Lamy "The Life and Letters of John Baptist Lamy, First Archbishop of Santa Fe," lecture, July 21, 1935., CFOM 5/12
      - Archbishop John B. Lamy Bulletin announcing a lecture by O'Malley re: Lamy, Sunday, July 21, 1935 Copies of Items in Lamy File, Loretto Motherhouse, Loretto, Kentucky, November 4, 1937. Photostats of some Lamy correspondence O'Malley's thesis on Lamy, Chapter I: The Giant Endurance Chapter II: The New Bishop of Santa Fe and His Vicar-General Chapter III: The Journey to Santa Fe Notes on Lamy and "Social Background of American Literature: Roman Catholicism and Non-Catholic Sects", CFOM 5/13
      - D.H. Lawrence- "The Modern Revolt Against Puritanism: D.H. Lawrence," Lecture, CFOM 5/14
      - D.H. Lawrence "D.H. Lawrence," lecture "Lawrence's Denial of the Intellect," lecture "The Religion of D.H. Lawrence," by John William Meaney, B.A. Thesis, U. of Notre Dame, Department of English, June, 1940., CFOM 5/15
      - Literary Criticism Principles and Methods of Literary Criticism A History of Literary Criticism, CFOM 5/16
      - Literature "The Literature of This Century: A Literature of Agony" "IX, Hovering," poem by unidentified author "Present Turning Points in American Life: Literature", CFOM 5/17
      - Literature "The Present State of Literature," lecture Notes, CFOM 5/18
      - Literature and Religion Special Lectures: "Modern Literature and the Religious Attitude to Life," Handwritten and typed copies. Program: Religion and the Crisis of the Twentieth Century, April 22, 1953, Symposium, CFOM 5/19
      - Liturgy and Literature Liturgy and Literature: Lecture I (missing one page) Liturgy and Literature: Lecture II: Three Modern German Catholics, Adam, Guardini, Von Hildebrand (Liturgical Roots), CFOM 5/20
      - John Locke "John Locke: Idealist? Realist?" lecture "John Locke: His Sensism," lecture "John Locke: Finale," lecture "The Triumph of Scientism and Naturalism," lecture "Alexander Pope and Nature," lecture, CFOM 5/21
      - Robert Lowell "Robert Lowell: The Mills of the Kavanaughs," review, CFOM 5/22
      - Nature of Art Manuscript Untitled manuscript by unidentified author (probably O'Malley) Re: the Nature of Art, Mauriac, Silone, and Kafka, CFOM 6/01
      - Nature of Art Manuscript untitled manuscript by unidentified author (probably O'Malley) Chapters I (The Nature of Art) and III (Kafka), CFOM 6/02
      - Nature of Art Manuscript Untitled manuscript by unidentified author (probably O'Malley) Chapter II (Silone), CFOM 6/03
      - Nature of Art Manuscript Untitled manuscript by unidentified author (probably O'Malley) Chapter IV (Mauriac), CFOM 6/04
      - Marian Poetry "Marian Poetry of Charles L. O'Donnell: Approaches and Notes" Hopkins, The Blessed Virgin Compared to the Air We Breathe" Peguy, "The Passion of Our Lady" Chesterton, "The Arena", CFOM 6/05
      - Marxism "The Marxian Interpretation of History and Society," lectures, 3 Parts. Excerpts on "Socialism and Society," by George H. Dune, The Commonweal, Vol. 43, November 23, 1945, pp. 134-39. "Dostoevsky and Revolution," Unidentified student paper, CFOM 6/06
      - Mauriac- first four pages of a lecture on Mauriac, CFOM 6/07
      - "Francis Mauriac (some quick observations)", CFOM 6/08
      - Thomas Merton, notes, CFOM 6/09